由於工作方嘅內容咧。
誒英聯邦。
我哋夠人又夠鐘啦，噉我哋可以開始會議。
以前第三行係關於咩咧？就係英國誒英聯邦會議。
OK，如果冇問題咧，我哋就去以前第三行。
噉啊！以前第一行就係上次會議發出嘅文件。
係屬誒屬於工商事務委員會嘅職權範圍。
噉啊！以前第二項就係下次開會嘅時間同埋討論嘅事項。
噉啊！我哋下個例會咧，將會係六月十五號星期二嘅下午兩點三十分舉行。
咁呢個邀請咧，就交咗為本會去畀事務委員會考慮嘅。
誒，除咗今次開會嘅會議文件之外咧，秘書處係冇發出其他嘅討論文件嘅。
咁秘書處咧就喺五月十一號咧就發出咗通報，就詢問是否有議員有興趣參加呢個工作坊。
聯合會英國分會舉辦嘅貿易協議虛擬工作方嘅係列，探討跨太平洋夥伴全面進展協協定。
誒建議嘅討論事項就包括係國家十四五嘅規劃，同埋咧第二就係研發中心嘅二零一九至二零二零年度同埋二零二零二零二一年度嘅進度報告，大家有冇問題？
議會聯合會英國分會咧就邀請我哋立法會議員參加，將於本年嘅六月十四、十七、二十一同埋二十八日喺網上舉行嘅貿易協定虛擬嘅工作坊嘅係列。
截至到截止日期屆滿咧，就只有我一位係表示有興趣參加嘅。而家請委員同意以下嘅事項：第一係咪接受英聯邦會議會嘅聯合會英國分會嘅邀請，同埋第二咧？
好。
副局，簡介一下，好嘛？
大家冇問題，多謝。噉啊！
噉啊！我哋而家邀請啊！
噉我係而家邀請政府嘅官員入呢個會議室。
係提名本人參加工作方，大家有冇問題？
噉啊！以前第四行咧，就係香港參與一帶一路嘅建設。
好啊！啊，主席，各位委員，大家好。今日我聯同一帶一路專員。
事實上，國家主席習近平啦，喺今年四月博鰲亞洲論壇嘅開幕式上面啦，亦都係提及。
我就會代表立法會去參加呢個會議，到時就會彙報翻畀大家知個會議嘅內容。
就住一帶一路倡議，佢係歡迎誒有興趣嘅經濟體去共同參與、共同合作、共同獲益。
誒，同各位就住商經局過去一年喺推動一帶一路建設方面嘅策略同埋措施，以及啦，我哋未來一啲嘅工作方向。
噉啊，當局曾經咧就喺二零二零年嘅二月咧，就同本事務委員會咧就提交過一帶一路建設嘅文件。咁而喺今次咧就再。
向委員會咧就彙報相關嘅工作嘅進展。噉我哋而家今日開會議咧，就有副商務及經濟發展局副局長陳百李博士，同埋一帶一路專員陳成輝博士，同埋一帶一路副專員李基順先生。
咁大家都知道啦，一帶一路倡議啦，現今已經係邁進第八年。目前國家已經係同超過一百七十個經濟體或者係國際機構去簽署咗合作文件。咁喺呢方面咧，亦都係説明咗一帶一路倡議啦，係非常之得到國際社會嘅認同同埋支持。
特區政府咧一直以嚟咧都係致力推動社會各界積極咁去參與一帶一路嘅建設㗎，而發揮香港所長，貢獻國家所需。事實上啦，今年三月通過嘅國家十四五規劃綱要裏邊啦，國家係明確支持香港參與。
打造共建一帶一路功能平台。
參與啦，同埋建立夥伴合作關係。
我哋共同去開拓機遇、發展機遇㗎。
統中心同埋四個新興中心呢個功能同埋角色。
助力國家全面開放和現代化經濟體係建設。
咁呢方面嘅工作啦，係可以推動香港疫後我哋嘅經濟發展同埋社會發展。
咁本屆政府啦，係採取一個叫做全政府動員嘅方針，去推展香港參與一帶一路嘅建設工作嘅。
咁唔同嘅政策局啦，亦都係就住佢哋相關嘅範疇啦，去提升核心競爭力，去發揮促進者同埋推廣者嘅角色。
促進資金流通，去推動香港作為建設一帶一路投融資嘅平台，將外資同埋人才啦係引進來。
光要同時啦，係肯定咗香港喺國際金融、商貿、航運同埋法律及解決爭議服務中心呢四個傳統中心嘅地位同角色。
咁呢方面嘅支持啦，係不單止為我哋香港嘅經濟發展係及時咁打入咗一支強心針，另外咧亦都係對我哋一帶一路方面嘅工作啦係注入新嘅動力。
咁大家亦都清楚啦，一帶一路倡議咧個重點係希望去加強相關嘅經濟體或者係地區之間嘅設施聯通、貿易暢通同埋資金融通等等。
光耀裏邊咧，係更加加入支持香港去發展成為國際航空樞紐、國際嘅創科中心、區內嘅知識產權貿易中心同埋中外文化藝術交流中心呢四個新興中心嘅地位。換言之，光耀啦係支持香港四個全。
咁香港作為國家嘅國際門户，同埋全球離岸人民幣業務嘅樞紐，我哋可以喺多方面善用我哋國際化同埋專業化嘅優勢，大力咁參與一帶一路嘅建設，包括就係提供各種同國際接軌嘅專業服務。
咁同時啦，香港係擁有誒大量嘅高端同埋同國際接軌嘅專業人才。咁喺呢方面啦，我哋係同內地嘅企業啦，共同走出去或者聯合走出去。我哋係佢哋一個好好嘅合作伙伴。咁所以喺呢方面啦，我哋係可以幫助到內地企業走向國際市場。
咁至於商經局啦，我哋除咗係做好一個統籌同協調嘅角色之外啦，我哋亦都係循住多方面去推進一帶一路嘅建設工作嘅。咁包括就係加強政策聯通啦，充分利用香港嘅優勢啦，利用好香港專業服務嘅定位角色啦，促進項目嘅。
去尋找商機。
國家商務部嘅支持。
項目或者係需求為本，去進行分分享或者係一啲嘅合作嘅對接。
咁喺疫情穩定之後啦，我哋係會聯同呢啲有興趣嘅企業啦，係到呢啲東盟國家嘅經貿合作區裏邊做實地考察嘅。
咁另外啦，我哋亦都不斷咁去擴大我哋嘅駐外經貿辦網絡。咁喺呢方面啦，我哋駐迪拜嘅經貿辦啦，預計可以喺今年年底之前啦，係可以投入服務。
咁另外咧，我哋亦都係會繼續舉辦我哋年度嘅「一帶一路」高峯論壇啦。咁包括就係舉辦誒好受歡迎嘅一啲嘅一對一嘅啊機會誒嘅嘅項目嘅對接誒對接會啦。
噉我哋亦都係會繼續支持啊，貿發局去向業界分享一帶一路方面嘅相關信息，同埋咧，我哋亦都係會支持企業去發展一帶一路嘅市場等等呢方面嘅工作嘅。
噉，正如文件裏邊亦都有提及啦，商經局喺一帶一路方面嘅工作啦，亦都係包括咗啊，譬如我哋舊年六月嘅係牽頭構建咗呢個抗疫創新科技產品與研發經驗分享及商機推廣平台。
咁商經局咧，亦都係積極尋求同唔同嘅經濟體去替做自由貿易協定同埋投資協定。咁喺呢方面，大家都清楚啦。我哋正喺度積極係喺RCEP生效之後啦，希望可以盡快加入。
嗱，包括就係剛剛喺上個禮拜五月十四號啦，我哋係聯同國資委係啟動咗呢個內地企業夥伴交流及對接計劃，並且咧，我哋係聯同香港中企協係舉辦咗啊呢個計劃下首場嘅交流會。
咁另外，我哋亦都係透過唔同嘅平台去促進內地企業同我哋香港企業啊、香港專業服務界別等等啊一齊去善用香港嘅國際經驗同埋我哋喺專業服務呢方面嘅優勢，發揮香港嘅專業喺一帶一路項目方面嘅軟實力。
譬如喺加強政策聯通呢方面啦，我哋同國家法改委喺二零一七年簽署咗支持香港參與一帶一路嘅安排。咁喺呢方面啦，我哋係正喺度跟進緊嗰個安排裏邊嗰六大範疇同二十六個措施誒當中嘅一啲嘅誒跟進嘅工作㗎。
咁當日嘅交流會啦，係有四十七間企業係參與，超過係一百位人士啦，係參加一個討論項目嘅。其中啦，我哋亦都係舉辦咗四十場嘅一對一嘅項目對接會，咁令到係企業啦可以係同香港嘅專業服務界別以項。
咁另外啦，我哋亦都係初步選定咗五個位於東盟國家嘅經貿合作區。噉我哋將會係以一個試點形式啦，去推動香港有興趣參與嘅企業係同嗰啲嘅經貿合作區係做一啲嘅對接嘅。咁而呢方面嘅計劃啦，亦都係得到。
噉就住呢個平台啦，我哋係幫助我哋嘅創科企業喺過去依年疫情期間啦，係推出一啲嘅創科產品啊，譬如係Covid十九test kit啊、線上網誒嘅嘅學習平台啊，啊又或者係五G智能嘅抗疫啊機械人等等嘅，係幫助佢哋咧喺疫情間啊，甚至乎疫情後啦。
咁另外咧，我哋亦都喺舊年嘅六月、八月同九月啦，係分別同泰國、印尼同馬來西亞政府啦，係舉辦咗一個網上嘅研討會嘅。噉就算喺疫情期間咧，我哋都透過一個線上模式去保持住我哋唔同經濟體之間嘅溝通同埋聯係。
倡議同埋。
就可以把握一帶一路。
我認為咧，事實係勝於勝於雄辯㗎。
誒粵港澳大灣區發展帶帶嚟嘅商機。
香港嘅資金流向咧，其實大家都睇到咧，係保持穩定。
其中，舊年香港有差唔多四百億。
誒香港誒繼續用好一國兩制嘅優勢。
嘅資金流入，營商環境咧繼續係穩定有序。
啊！對於啊，有外界質疑香港啊，而家有資金流出。
咁喺未來一年啦，我哋係會繼續用好香港作為獨特門户、作為跳板、作為中介人嘅角色。
與此同時咧，香港嘅法治係一個法治嘅社會，司法獨立亦都係香港賴以成功嘅基石。
繼續為業界喺構建更多嘅交流同埋對接嘅嘅嘅機會，係幫助我哋業界啦，去把握一帶一路建設啦所衍生嘅一啲嘅商機嘅。
咁規劃光耀裏邊啦，係支持香港打造建設一帶一路嘅功能平台。咁喺呢方面啦，係對香港喺相關嘅優勢同埋我哋嘅能力呢方面啦，係進一步肯定嘅。
就係CB庫一八九零縮二十二十一庫零四號文件嘅，噉我而家咧就誒開放畀委員嘅發問，因為時間充足，噉我暫時就唔設限時間先。第一位係林建峯議員。好，誒多謝主席。
主席、各位委員，國家喺十四五期間啊，係會加快形成以國內大循環為主體、國際國內雙循環相互促進嘅新嘅發展格局。而喺呢個格局底下啦，香港將會係迎來好大嘅機遇。而國家喺十四五，
以下落嚟啦，我同我同事啦係樂意聽取大家嘅意見同埋建議啦，去回應大家嘅查詢。多謝主席。好啊，唔該啊，副局。噉我補充翻咧，政府當局提供咗嘅討論文件咧，就係立法會C.B.庫一八九零縮二十廿一庫零三號文件，同埋秘書處就準備咗啲背景資料嘅文件咧。
我。
嗱，呢個內循環。
外部勢力唔應該對。
一個航運中心嚟到。
嗱，香港嘅疫情咧都算係平穩。
我哋想問一問政府啦，嗱雖然。
啊嘅聯繫㗎，咁但係香港。
誒做一啲誒招商或者走出去嘅。
內地抗疫成績咧，亦都有目共睹。
香港同新加坡呢個旅遊氣泡咧，就係再度延延後。
依法判刑嘅案件，指指點點，霍爾木特克。
對於我哋嗰個經濟發內地嘅發展咧，好有利㗎。噉我哋香港，
有關嘅誒工商或者專業界嘅公司咧，嚟到一齊合作咧。
啲你正話亦都講到啦，即係而家內地搞呢個內循環同埋雙循環啦。
又點樣去善用？我哋有冇善用國內我哋依啲機會，即係自動主動啊，去國內揾依啲？
咁誒，正話誒，局長都講到咧，就話內地好多嘅工商業啦，都會善用香港呢個金融中心。
找緊。
搞幾次都搞唔成。
以配合同埋。
呢個深圳前海大灣區發展嘅機遇。
而家正話，我講個氣泡，氣泡咧，其實。
噉啊嗱，因為依個咧，我都要講講㗎啦。
既然我哋個疫情穩定嘅咧，最重要都係嗰個關頭可以開得到。
我哋最關心嘅咧，就係我哋同國內通關嗰個問題。
嗱，有乜嘢你哋可以做到？做到之後咧，你哋有有啲咩可以做得到嘅？
都覺得應該包埋香港嘅，因為我哋中國不可分割嘅一部分啊嘛。
特別係喺一啲招商活動嗰度，正話局長佢哋都提到咧，啊，嗰個一對一好成功嘅，而家一對一係好難做嘅，除非係網上嘅啫。咁喺呢一方面，
噉啊嗱，即係依個點樣？我我哋有啲咩可以做到咧？嗱，當局響未來會唔會或者點樣集中火力，用好做好香港嘅優勢，特別係響工商專業服務嗰方面咧？
你哋可以做啲咩嚟到補誒補充嚇好嘛？啊，唔該，主席。好啊，唔該，副局。好多謝主席，多謝阿林議員嘅意見同埋建議。誒，就住剛才你所講嘅一個一對一嘅對接會啦。嗱，當然喺過去呢年疫情期間，啊，我哋就係未必能夠。
做咗啲嘅實體去出外去做一啲嘅外訪考察啦，咁但係喺過去依一年啦，就算係咁嚴峻嘅環境底下，我哋咧透過一個線上模式啊，儘量透過呢個係啊線上啊線上嘅模式啦，係去做好呢方面嘅對接工作。咁另外咧，我亦都好同意剛才啊林議員所講嘅，誒嚟緊誒一帶一路倡議又好，大灣區。
區規劃又好啊，以致內循環都好啦。其實呢呢幾方面啦，都係國家一個係經濟發展一個重要嘅策略，誒，亦都係我哋所講嘅，尤其是大灣區啊、一帶一路啊，就係國家經濟發展嘅一個叫雙引擎啦。咁而事實上啦，一帶一路同埋大灣區啦，係一個內外互相推動嘅策略嚟嘅。
誒係啊，專員。
試點咧，就係畀香港嘅公事。
等等呢啲咁嘢，即係我哋會做到啲乜嘢咧？即係唔係就係話誒，我同中央叫中央幫我哋手去做呢樣嗰樣，有啲咩實質嘅嘢係幫到我哋香港嘅公司？
誒依個初創企業嘅誒範疇啦，咁過去其實因為我哋出唔到去啦，我哋同誒貿發局亦都有合作，就係上年做咗誒三個誒急軍到急民政府同政府嘅對接。
咁第二點咧就係頭先誒亦都提過，就係專業嘅誒誒誒機構啦。咁專業機構其實我哋上個禮拜都做咗一個同國資委合辦嘅誒對接交流，係喺誒線下嘅，即係咁咧就差唔多有誒四十個一對一嘅會議啦。
噉啊！大家都知道啦，啊，內地大灣區裏邊咧個經濟活力係相當之好嘅。而喺一帶一路倡議當中啦，嗱，我哋究竟係增強咗啲咩嘢咧？其實一帶一路咧就係會增加嗰個金融投資啦、航運嘅物流啦、基礎嘅建設啦、專業嘅服務啦啊，同埋貿易等等產業嘅需求，而呢啲。
呢啲產業咧，正正就喺香港、喺大灣區，以致喺內地啦，我哋嘅獨特優勢所在。所以喺推動一帶一路嘅建設過程當中啦，我哋係會繼續發揮一個叫做引進來、走出去嘅角色，成為內地啊，尤其是大灣區嘅企業啦，係借用香港呢個平台去走出去。
同時間咧，亦都係借用香港呢啲平台咧，引入外資進入大灣區以至內地呢個雙向平台嘅。咁所以嚟緊，我哋會係喺聯合走出去啊呢個工作方面啊，係會加強同內地嘅企業去合作嘅。其實喺二零一九年啦，我哋亦都係同商務部同埋一啲嘅國企啊。
央企啊，一齊去到誒誒誒中歐一啲嘅啊誒嘅國家啦，去共同去做呢啲嘅呢個叫做共同走出去呢啲呢啲嘅項目嘅。另外，我再回應阿林議員剛才所講嘅嚟緊，我哋點樣樣係同中央啊一齊去做好喺一帶一路方面嘅工作啦。咁其實文言裏邊有提。
提及啦，誒，我哋好多嘅企業啊，其實係好有興趣去加入「一帶一路」完善經濟體，尤其是係東盟市場嘅一啲嘅經貿合作園區嘅。咁所以喺呢方面咧，我哋亦都係係好積極咁同商務部啦，係加強聯繫。噉啊，希望啦喺個入園嘅一個準則啊，或者條款方。
方面啦，或者去了解個經營環境啊咁方面啦，我哋係會加強喺呢方面嘅工作嘅。今年稍後啦，我哋都會邀請呢啲嘅公務園區啦嘅代表嚟到香港啊，或者咧係透過線上形式啦，係去講解翻畀我哋業界聽啊，究竟啲園區啦嗰個誒進入條件啊，或者優惠條款係咩嘢？咁所以喺呢方面嘅工作咧，我。
我哋係會繼續做好區嘅。主主席啊，係即係幫幫國內嘅企業走出去啊，同埋幫啊外國嘅企業咧引進去國內啦。我哋成日都聽到㗎啦，但係局長回應嗰度都冇一一啲實際嘅回應咧，就係話喂，你點幫到香港嘅公司？
係嘛？響兩方邊，你淨係話喂，你香港誒舉辦一啲誒研討會啊、介紹會啊，咁響香港點樣幫香港嗰啲公司？而家我哋成日講咧，就話前海未來個發展好好好嘅橫琴嗰方邊，亦都有一個誒粵澳深化嘅嘅協議嘅。
好。
嗯。
跟住阿姚思榮議員。
大大大膽噉樣就提出呢個支援措施。
我就航空輸流，嚇咁誒珠三角嚇，譬如誒深圳啊、廣州啊。
好簡單就頭先，我哋誒作作為呢個航空樞紐，香港而家打造緊一個誒誒機場城市。
啊！甚至澳門啊，佢哋都會喺睇到未來個發展空間，佢哋會提升佢哋嘅競爭力，同香港帶嚟直接嘅誒呢個威脅或者挑戰。
咁咧，誒推動咗誒唔同嘅公司咧，就係可以去到東南亞嘅唔同國家咧，就係做到呢啲誒，尤其是疫情下邊嘅技術型嘅公司，好似誒嗰啲誒誒誒。
政策上喺實質支援上，政府可唔可以就真係好似內地噉樣？只要你呢個嘅企業，你呢個嘅投資係幫到呢個城市，幫到我哋香港，喺一啲做法上做真係做誒？
誒唔係叫投訴啦，就話喂誒有個誒航天城，佢哋希望政府回應一下整個路牌，即係到時候有個指示咁啦。去到航天城點去啊？噉樣幾個禮拜政府都唔回應嘅，即係我覺得政府係可喺喺呢啲噉嘅例子之下。
喺呢方面，我第一個問題就問政府有冇考慮到喺一帶一路嘅建設入面，香港我哋睇到比較好嘅比較多，有冇啲行業因為呢個建設，我哋收受到周邊嘅挑戰，呢啲行業政府有冇一個扶持嘅政策咧？
誒機械人啦，誒依個誒體温量度啊，誒依個殺菌塗塵啊檢測系統，依啲都係香港嘅公司，佢哋亦都找到依個東南亞唔同地區嘅生意。咁依啲係依啲誒幾個實體嘅例子。
誒主席議員誒，或者我補充誒，頭先誒議員問又有咩實質例子啦？咁誒，其實我哋誒幫香港嘅公司喺呢個一帶一路倡議咧，主要係三方面嘅類型嘅公司啦。第一類型就係可能係誒已經喺中國有廠。
想出去睇下係咪喺東南亞地區或者其他地區去設廠嘅咁？我哋其實同商務部亦都誒做咗五個試點啦。頭先阿局長都講過啦，咁亦都係誒經過唔同嘅資訊、唔同嘅平台，包括誒貿發局嘅平台咧，就係誒將呢啲噉嘅推介嘅。
咁依個對接會咧，其實我哋就係將誒香港嘅金融、香港嘅保險業，誒舉一個例子，就係譬如誒誒依個誒香港作為一個風險管理中心啦。其實經過我哋唔同依個法改委唔同嘅溝通咧，香港。
已經係誒成為依個四個國內保險業嘅風險管理中心嘅誒舉聚腳點，所以依啲就係可以幫助香港嘅具體業務啦。第三樣例子就係誒我哋嘅誒技術或者我哋叫做誒。
誒多謝主席。誒參與一帶一路嘅建設咧，當然對我哋香港長遠有利啦。嚇，噉啊頭先啊副局所講嘅，我哋嘅專業服務啦、投融資啦或者貿易咧，誒對我哋未來嘅發展會帶嚟好大空間。噉啊，亦睇到政府喺創科方面。
投入抌咗唔少資源啦，嚇！希望通過扶持香港創科咧，使到香港喺誒大灣區入面，甚至喺成個第一一大路咧入面咧，我有個起到重要嘅角色。但有利必有弊嘅，嚇！誒喺參與一大路入面咧，我覺得咧，香港一啲行業會受到影響，譬如。
國家支持翻香港嘅企業喺呢個方面嘅。
啊！咁另外，我哋亦都係透過一啲嘅合作園區啦。剛才阿專員同我都有講過啦。咁喺呢方面啦，點樣可以幫助到我哋企業啦去落地啦？咁呢方面亦都係會繼續做好呢方面嘅工作嘅。
係，誒，姚舒榮議員有冇？主席啊，嗱，兩個問題有冇答案？第一個喺一帶一路政策之下，我哋香港咩行業會受到影響？政府有咩政策上嘅支持？
由以往嘅只係淨係可以支援內地嘅項目啦，就係到而家係同香港簽訂貿易協定同埋投資保障協定嘅三十七個經濟體，而當中咧好多都係喺一帶一路沿線嘅啊經濟體嗰度嘅。
咧會總結好似今次第一次會嘅成果，然後畀大家作為一個參照。咁對大家推行推行嘅時候，大家有啲政策啊，有啲投資，大家有明確咧。咁有呢方面有冇一啲實質嘅推進嘅一啲具體內容或者時間表咧？噉樣。
機場城市入面咧有唔少嘅建設咧，都係一可能都係一啲私人參與。以往政府咧，往往都係話啊，私人參與，政府就誒驚咗㗎官商勾結，而係避忌咧去作出直接嘅政策上嘅一啲支援。啊，咁最近我誒收到個即係。
咁誒，所以第二個問題就係呢方面，政府有冇打破以往靠官商勾結而對出一啲嘅支援咧，可以大膽啲咧噉樣。第三個問題就係頭先講嘅，就係同一啲誒喺國聯同國資委同香港中國企業協會啦，你哋五月十四號搞咗一個嘅有關嘅交流會啦。嗱，交流。
會咧，我覺得應該係實質嘅意義嘅，但係誒點樣去睇到咩成果咧？誒有冇一個嘅誒，即係總結嘅誒一個噉嘅安排咧？譬如誒今次第一次啦，咁會第二次，第二次除咗誒可能會誒就繼續誒提出發展嘅方向之外。
係嘅，或者我先嘗試答呢個問題，有陣間阿專員可以再補充。誒，回應阿姚議員所講啦，首先就係話點樣樣去具體咁去幫助我哋啲項目，或者幫助我哋嘅行業啦。其實我會分三個方面啦。第一就係首先喺個資訊嗰方面嘅，即係我哋要了解翻究竟一帶一路嘅項。
項目究竟係有乜嘢？譬如我哋頭先所講嘅一啲嘅專業服務啊，究竟香港可以提供乜嘢嘅企業啊，或者專業服務嘅優勢啦。另外就係話，我哋要睇翻一啲嘅投資唔同嘅項目。咁所以喺呢方面啦，我哋有個T D C嘅belt and road belt belt and road嘅portal啦，一個係資訊嘅網站啦。嗱，當中就係羅列咗誒有。
有三百幾個啊！我哋一啲嘅相關嘅專業服務啦，同埋有六百幾個相關嘅投資項目。咁喺呢方面咧，就做好一個資訊嘅對接。咁所以呢個係第一方面啦。第二嘅就係話喺一個啊誒合作對接呢方面嘅啊，即係話我哋係會聯同有興趣參與一帶一路項目嘅。
無論係專業服務又好，無論係生產製造業又好，又或者係初創企業都好啦。我哋係會帶同佢啊，疫情之後咧係一齊去去外訪，或者去參與一啲嘅項目對接。咁所以喺呢方面咧，我哋亦都會做足呢方面嘅工作。到到最後一方面咧，就係嗰支援嗰方面啦。咁當然呢方面咧。
我哋一方面係會同國家嘅相關部委啊，包括啊國資委又好啊，商務部又好啦，喺一啲嘅合作或者對接交流嘅平台，繼續做好呢方面工作啦。另外，我哋亦都係會喺我哋一啲嘅支援平台，譬如喺北分嗰度啦。咁大家都知道啦，我哋最近亦都係放寬咗北分嘅資助地域範。
係。
跟住，跟住，蔣麗雲議員。
基建嘅項目咧，其實係不多嘅，咁所以我哋個誒配對咧，其實係希望呢啲央企出去一第一路做呢個基建嘅時候咧。
佢同埋諗住對接乜嘢咧？咁咁下一步我哋有啲咩計劃咧？因為你就嚟又話搞個噉嘅誒呢個對誒對接誒交流一啲噉嘅論壇係嘛？咁咁可可唔可以請局方介紹一下，講講咧？
嘅記憶中應該有五五至六個會議，就係包括同誒金管局啊，包括同保險業界啊，包括同依個誒專業團體啊。咁譬如今年一月份，我哋都做咗個叫保穩定、謀發展同央企打造一帶一路嘅功能平台。
誒，我誒誒誒副局冇係呢方面係直接回應到嘅。第二個對一啲嘅企業，當佢需要支持嘅時候喺政策上，政府可唔可以打破以往拍孤商勾結而唔夠膽提出一啲直接支援嘅措施？喺內地就好清楚嘅，只要你係幫得到咧，佢。
就唔會有呢個擔心，但係香港往往有呢個擔心喺呢兩個國誒誒呢呢兩個問題上，希望誒副局能夠清晰啲，影下第三個問題都未答，就係就頭先講啦啊，即係呢個喺國資委誒同埋中國企業會喺五月十四號開會之後，喺嗰個未來嗰個。
個具體跟進方面有冇一啲時間表啊，或者具體做法咧？啊，呢三個問題都冇直接回應到。係報告，請啊專業員。誒，主席議員，我嘗試回答誒三個問題啦。誒，第一個問題就係誒關於譬如我哋喺誒誒一帶一路倡。
以上邊有誒唔同跟國內嘅競爭性嗰陣時，我哋點樣支持翻業界啦？咁其實我哋每年都有依個誒誒同國資委同埋有十三個部門嘅誒聯席會議嘅。咁聯席會議嗰度咧，其實有誒唔同嘅項目，我哋都會提出，就係希望。
咁誒，依個第第一個問題啦。第二個問題係關於誒誒政府會唔會去支持特定嘅某一個企業誒去一帶一路嘅地方咯？咁其實我哋已經誒嘗試突破關關嘅。如果你睇翻我哋嗰個抗疫平台誒，可能。
以前人哋會覺得誒得十幾個香港嘅抗疫企業，你係咪淨係支持呢十幾個，唔支持其他咧？噉我哋都照嘗試誒走出呢個框框誒，做咗三個誒government to government政府同政府嘅會議，係跟泰國、馬來西亞同埋印尼舉。
揾大臂。
想嘅，咁所以呢個就係我哋點解啊揀選呢五個園區嗰個原因。
睇翻個上下游啊，各方面造廠嘅形式，咁所以我哋都係希望做翻個平台，就係有誒覺得需要嘅、覺得有幫助嘅，我哋可以要求誒商務部睇可唔可以畀翻同等優惠畀我哋。
媒體咧做完嗰個會議之後咧，亦都通過誒貿發局嗰個一帶一路平台咧，就係咧再有一個一對一嘅對接。所以如果你問翻嗰十幾間公司嚟講咧，佢係覺得政府係誒有全力嘅支持佢。咁第三個問題就係關於誒。
係我哋五月十四號做咗嗰個誒同郭之威嘅會議，誒究竟有咩成效，有咩具體實質嘅成效咧？首先回應翻議員，就其實我哋唔係淨係做一個會議嘅。誒舉例就係同郭之偉嚟講，其實我哋喺誒過去三年其實已經做咗誒以我。
咁五月十四號咧，我哋就第一次嘗試咧，就做翻個線下嘅會議，因為過去兩年做呢個線上嘅會議咧，誒都做得太多啦。咁所以咧，其實我哋咧有誒四十七家企業咧係有唔同嘅對接嘅。噉我哋都揾咗央企。
七個代表包括長江三合集團啦、電力中電啦、中國鐵路工程啦、中國石油天然啦、中國交通建設啦，同埋中港國際控股。咁如果你聽到呢七個央企咧，你就知道佢哋其實係做基建為主嘅。咁香港去一帶一路嘅地方做基。
業界即係我哋嘅專業團隊，包括金融、包括保險、包括律師團隊咧，係可以我哋叫聯合走出去又好，並船出海又好，可以同依啲噉嘅基建項目咧係掛鈎，可以係誒香港嘅企業咧得到一些。
誒幫助，咁所以咧誒，我哋今次咧誒，包括呢個四十個一對一對接咧，我哋聽到業界嘅聲音咧，就係包括保險業同金融業咧，尤其是係見到有好多機會咧，會跟進。咁至於點樣跟進咧？其實我哋喺誒誒上年。
年六月份咧，亦都喺貿發局嗰度咧，誒做咗第二版嘅一帶一路嘅誒網上平台。咁呢個平台咧，其實我哋做咗之後咧，喺個基建平台度咧已經有一千三萬萬嘅誒瀏覽量。咁咧，佢個誒。
項目咧有六百三廿幾個，而依六百三廿幾個項目咧係誒唔係一個滾一路滾出嚟嘅number嚟嘅，因為佢誒個項目冇咗之後咧就會取消。咁一路其實我哋依啲項目咧喺貿發局依個平台嗰度咧，其實都會見到啲成果，誒見到啲成。
誒，即係跟跟一句啫，好嘛？好嗱，就誒頭先講，即係我哋香港作為港輸樓個挑戰咧，係好明顯嘅。咁或者會後我同商建局傾傾啦，即係譬如將來香港嘅國際機場三跑開咗之之後咧，我哋面臨嘅挑戰有乜嘢地方咧？政府我作出支援，我哋交流下啦，好嘛？好啊！
唔該，主席。啊，主席，我想問一問就誒，我睇文件咧就詳細情況有關啱啱啊，局方就講咧就選定咗有五個對接地區啦，泰國柬埔寨、馬來西亞、印尼噉，印尼裏邊有兩個區嘅。噉我我想問下誒，點解點解會選咗呢五個地？
好啊，阿副局，我嘗試回答先啦。啊，多謝啊，蔣議員嘅提問。啊，首先點解係要揀選？啊，點解會揀選咗呢五個啊園區咧？咁其實之前啦，我哋係同貿發局同埋誒商會啦，或者企業代表啦，係其實做咗一個survey啦，就係就住佢哋一啲嘅運作需要啊，包括一啲。
啲嘅設備嘅配套啊、物流嘅支援啊，或者上下游產業嘅配合，就住呢方面啦。究竟佢哋係需要啲咩嘢咧？同埋我哋要睇翻呢啲園區一啲嘅優惠政策啊，同埋當地嘅營商環境等等。而就住呢樣嘢咧，我哋亦都係come up回覆啦，就係話剛才所講啦，喺泰國、馬來西亞引嚟柬埔寨啊呢～
四個地方嘅五個園區裏邊，噉我哋就商務部啦，係有個共識，就係話咧嚟緊，如果香港企業有興趣嘅企業啦，包括譬如好似做電子業啊、電器業啊，或者玩具業等等，佢哋有興趣去進入呢啲園區嘅話咧，我哋將會係能夠同園方或者係啲合作區裏邊嘅管理人員啊，或者其他可以做一個更緊密嘅聯。
係就住園區裏邊嘅政策環境啊、投資環境啊，又或者入園嘅優惠啦，去喺呢方面啦，係做多啲嘅工作嘅。咁另外，即係點解會揀選阿時人呢幾個地方啦？咁其實大家都知道啦，我哋喺二零一七年同誒東盟啦係有個貿易協定啦、投資保障協定啦。咁呢方面嘅工作啦，其實喺今年二月份啊呢個。
十二月。
我我哋其實做個個survey係揀咗三個行業嘅，包括電子、電子零件同埋依個誒紡織業。我哋誒嗰個survey嗰個文件，我哋再再補充翻。
嘅優即係嘅優惠做咗出嚟，或者有幾多嘅專業界別嘅人士係喺一帶一路裏邊咧，受到呢啲噉嘅優惠，你都不如做翻個個文件做翻嚟表畀我。跟住有周浩鼎議員㗎。
不過噉啊，仲有兩位誒議員咩？不過阿朱員，你可唔可以跟住咧？你畀翻嗰啲文件我，係分門別類，即係有咩廠家去邊度有興趣，或者正話張麗雲議員話嗰啲專業人士有幾多量化嘅？
係咪嚇？噉啊特別嗰度咁多誒基建啊、相關啊、建築嗰啲噉嘅嘢係嘛？譬如測量啊，噉啊啊啊architecture即係好多㗎嘛，係咪嚇？咁咁噉，你哋話好多機會，噉我想問由嗰陣時到而家啦，已經三年，唔知有啲咩機會咧？
FTA咧係全面生效嘅，咁變咗。如果香港企業係有興趣進入呢啲園區嘅，或者進入呢啲東盟國家嘅，咁首先嚟講，佢哋就會係受到呢一份FTA嘅保障。噉啊，變咗喺佢哋入去嘅一啲嘅入場嘅或者進入嘅門檻啊，啊或者係入去嘅一啲條款啊，係相對地係比較理。
或者主席，我補補充補充一句啊。誒，議員其實誒，如果你睇翻商務部咧，佢喺誒國外咧有一百一十個佢哋叫做certify嘅園區嘅。咁依一百一十個certify園區咧，其實我哋做過，頭先啊局長講過，就係我哋做過個篩選同埋一個。
誒同商會嘅survey，咁咧就係誒，因為我哋做唔到一百一十個咁多啦，亦都有啲太遠啦，噉就挑選咗亞視人依幾個地方，就四個國家、五個園區，誒柬埔寨、印尼、啊泰國同馬來西亞。咁依四個園區嘅特色咧，就係其實商務部已經。
傾咗啲條件咧，係傾咗成十幾廿年㗎啦。咁包括啲條件，包括係誒有咩税務優惠啊，三加三加三啊，有好多唔同嘅優惠咧。其實已經係畀咗國內嘅企業嘅。咁但係香港嘅企業咧就仲未得到呢個誒優惠嘅。噉我哋希
希望藉助於五個園區咧，就係誒希望商務部誒共同誒畀翻國內嘅所有優惠畀我哋。咁所以，我哋做完呢個survey之後咧，如果香港啲企業有興趣去嗰邊開廠嘅咧，我哋係可以誒通過香港政。
政府咧要求商務部咧就希望可以攞翻同等畀國內嘅誒優惠，咁亦都有一個保障作用就係，因為嗰邊嗰啲園區咧，佢成個體係包括啲保安啊，包括啲銀中國嘅銀行啊，誒包括所有嘅配套都齊嘅，咁但係就唔係每一個企業都適用嘅，因為要。
啊，張麗華，資源有冇嘢跟進？哎呀，嗱，我即係你而家你話，而家香港人假如去呢五個地區嘅園區裏邊投資嘅話咧，佢哋就享受唔到阿Sir嗰個協議裏邊嘅優惠，係咪啊？唔係唔係唔係，咁咪係咯，我唔使乜理啫，我自己去投資，同佢哋傾，佢都唔知幾welcome啊！
唔係，因為而家國家已經傾好曬啲條件，咁喺香港嘅企業去到咧就會跟國內其他嘅企業嘅條件一樣啊。係咯，咁都係受惠嘅。係咯，咪已經受惠嘅咯。係咯，係咯，咁冇問題。O K，冇問題。唔係啊，我即係話O K，即係誒而家其實咧就。
已經咧就接受有噉嘅優惠啦。OK，噉嘅話咧，咁其實咧咁商界咧亦都未必一定嚇應要要輸政府而去呢啲地區係咪？反而咧，我其實真係好關心咧。我哋上一次亦都問過啦，問個當局，譬如話有啲嗱，其實其實一帶一路裏邊咧。
最誒最最多嘅嘅嘅嘅嘅生意係乜嘢？就係嗰啲誒，即係建設啊嚇，建設做得最多。其實我諗係香港好多嗰啲專業人士咧，佢哋係最感興趣嘅。咁而家我想問下啦，嗱，我上一次都問咗㗎啦，喺五月十八號啊，唔係，sorry。
咦係九號有一個會議，咁咧就係誒誒呢個sorry係二零一八年嘅四月廿七號會議，我哋亦都有提過嘅。咁咧就係話喂，咁而家嗰個一帶一路咧，噉我哋啲專業人士啊，點樣可以有機會去發展咧？
誒，其實周浩鼎議員。
我呢個係意見嚟㗎，唔該，主席。冇冇錯啊，周定議員係咪可以稍後畀翻啲啲資料我哋啊？
咁喺誒依個網站推出以嚟，其實已經有一千五百三十萬嘅瀏覽人次，八十四個percent咧喺香港境外同埋香港嘅合作。
我覺得其實誒會唔會可以喺一段時間之內，你能唔能夠可以即係唔係叫你而家答啦？可能你翻去要要做啲預備功夫咧，稍後有冇機會可以提供翻畀我哋知道咧？書面嘅，即係可能有啲統計量化一下，例如話我舉個例。
有冇人已經去咗嗰度做緊咧？何專業？誒，我或者打翻你前面嗰個問題，再答你後邊嗰個問題啊，葉。誒，前面嘅問題其實誒，你嘅誒誒，我哋我哋嘅set up咧，其實咧，暫時如果香港嘅企業去到誒誒嗰個商務部指定嘅官員。
園區咧係未攞到啲優惠嘅，咁所以其實我哋係希望借住呢五個試點咧，就係話如果香港嘅企業，譬如佢哋係要去嗰邊開廠咧，希望好快噉樣，商務部可以支持呢啲優惠。咁呢個係誒希望我哋政府可以幫忙呢啲商界咧，就同商務部溝通。
攞到佢已經係差唔多全國最好嘅優惠，咁依個係第一點啦。即係誒補充翻。而家有優惠有定冇咧？而家呢幾個？而家你就咁行入去咧冇，因為好多企業其實誒誒自己去開廠，去越南開廠啊，柬埔寨開廠啊，佢有優惠，但係個優惠。
咧，其實係全國差唔多最好咧，都係商務部傾咗十幾年嘅優惠。噉佢而家行入去咧，係未必攞到嗰個優惠。咁所以，我哋希望通過政府同商務部嘅溝通咧，係幫助到佢咧攞到呢個優惠。多唔多廠家有興趣過去咧？嚇，多唔多廠家有興趣過去？好多廠。
廠家係有興趣，但係亦都佢哋要睇翻個行業，因為佢哋要睇翻個raw material喺邊度啊，運個raw material誒誒出嚟嘅成品點樣啊，個運輸點樣啊，所以其實每一個廠家咧depends on佢係誒做咩工業咧，其實對每國家嘅要求都。
誒回到你第二個問題，就係誒二零一八年講過誒，我哋啲專業嘅團隊點樣可以去到啲誒我哋叫基建項目啦。因為香港比較少誒公司係做誒一帶一路嘅基建項目咯。咁其實我哋誒辦公室亦都係。
朝住依個方向咧，依兩年都誒做咗好多嘢嘅。誒頭先提過就係第一，我哋係做咗個誒謀發局嘅一帶一路網站嘅第二版啦。咁依個第二版咧係包括一個叫做Infrastructure Toolkit一帶一路基建咁落。咁依個基建咁落。
當咧入邊咧，其實咧就係誒，包括嗰個公司型合作基礎嘅流程啊，亦都係有啲叫做免費嘅consultant，頭一段時間免費就係畀人哋走入去。譬如我係一個律師，我想去柬埔寨做一個基建嘅項目嘅話，我可以同。
簡報就係邊個律師團隊合作啊？誒咁依個誒Infrastructure Two Kit依個網站嘅其中一點就係專門誒，我哋希望可以誒補充到依個香港嘅專業團隊同埋國內入邊嘅基建項目嘅一個補充。
誒，唔該啊，主席。嗱，我睇文件咧，都其實誒都幾詳盡咁講介紹咗，即係啊，一帶一路專員你哋核下嘅相關嘅一啲嘅工作，包括即係就算咧疫情當中，你哋都誒有花心機去搞網上研討會啦，都有講咗，即係嗰啲研討會三場，比如話出席嘅人數。
即係六百、九百、八百五十人等等，又或者即係你，比如話推廣香港專業服務嘅一啲項目，噉你都話有個網站都列咗出嚟，有六百個項目喺一帶一路噉樣。噉我其實覺得呢啲當然都係需要，亦都啱做啦，要咁做嘅。咁但係我都誒想表達一個意見，即係好似頭先啊主席講咧。
啊！呢個你哋嘅呢啲相關嘅計劃推動咗之後，可能有幾多嘅香港公司嘅數字，無論參與過查詢個案嘅數字，或者到啊呢啲誒個案處理咗之後，或者佢哋成功喺當地獲篤咗啲項目。咁當然嗰啲項目有大有細啦，但係至少我哋都有個數。
知道咧幾多嘅公司已經喺嗰度當地咧攞咗啲項目去去處理，咁呢啲公司啊嘅大概可能你話僱員嘅人數啊等等有幾多係請咗香港人啊噉，其實即係如果有到呢啲嘢更加有效咁量化咧，又可以幫助你哋進一步解説畀啲公眾知道你哋。
啊！多謝主席。
噉我相信誒誒FSTB啊或者金管局嘅同事啦，係會繼續喺呢方面去推進嘅。
好啊，唔該。噉啊，最喺最後，我問少少問題添，因為誒大家知道一帶一路咧，而家就咁講出嚟，就算我哋睇咗文件咧。
希望得到你嘅支援，噉你又係可以有個記錄喺裏面咯。誒，呢個唔好嘥咗佢。我覺得呢個係好建議嚟嘅，周國定議員。係，好嘛。O.K.，跟住張華峯議員。
好冇？希望咧，即係能夠即係發揮我哋香港嘅金融中心嘅呢呢個優勢，去推動嗰個一帶一路嘅呢個發展。
最大嘅利用嘅人民辦業務嘅輸樓啊，可以幫助佢哋喺呢個籌集資金上發揮嘅作用。誒，但是而家到咗已經過咗四五年啦。
做嘅功夫，即係我誒，絕對唔係否定你哋做嘅工作。我見你哋都即係誒花咗好多嘅時間篇幅喺好多各種嘅連結啊、對接。頭先專員都解釋得好清楚嘅，即係例如話幫助我哋啲專業人士走出去啊，儘量跟多啲央企，可能佢哋如果喺嗰度有基建，用我哋專業人。
嘅服務啊，其實呢啲方向你哋做都啱嘅，只不過我就覺得如果有進一步有啲數字係量化到話咗畀佢聽咧，噉啊更加有效。舉一個例咧，而家喺啊啱啱呢個星期喺啊法司法事務委員會咧，同樣地都係講緊嗰個啊e-brand，即係例如話嗰個。
個啊網上嘅解決爭議嗰個中心咧，我哋都係問佢，佢都會稍有提供翻嘅。例如話，佢哋中間成立以嚟做過幾多個個案，有幾多單係成功咗，有幾多單係跟進緊？誒誒，嗰啲公司來自嘅係海外啊，定還是係內地大灣區或者係本地咧？佢哋都稍。
稍後有個breakdown畀翻我哋，咁所以咧，我我覺得呢個模式可以參考嘅，即係會唔會政府方面提供到呢啲詳盡嘅係數字嘅量化，咁大家更加知道咧喺推動我哋香港參與一帶一路，實實際際量到我哋嘅香港企業員工受惠嗰個量化，可以畀我哋睇清楚啲。
誒可以，其實誒我哋有個困難就係好多時啲誒誒誒企業咧，佢哋其實去咗邊個地方、大陸地方做咗依啲項目咧，佢未必翻嚟話翻畀政府聽嘅。所以其實就係點解我哋誒兩年前開始係誒通過依個貿發局。
嘅一帶一路平台咧，係想keep track翻呢啲項目嘅。咁所以想我哋稍後會補充翻，就係誒其實一路誒有項目誒一路喺度更新緊。咁嗰個貿發局嗰個網站嗰個項目誒數據庫咧，其實就係個項目，如果佢有一段時間唔喐咧，亦都
會係攞咗落嚟嘅，咁所以我哋有一個誒誒而家嘅項目嘅資料庫入邊，包括乜嘢項目、乜嘢專業團體。噉我哋到時再補充翻係嘛？我我我主席，我補充一點啫，即係誒，我都明白你可能有呢個困難，不過我覺得咧，會唔會你哋可以優化一下，即係稍後。
咧，你哋同呢啲機構，既然佢都用過我哋呢方面嘅服務啊，咁即係會唔會比較有效咁繼續跟蹤住，或者到時開寒問暖都問一問？因為因為點解咧？其實你甩咗就好嘥嘅，即係你花咗咁多時間去幫佢，我相信你哋都花咗資源、花咗心機去幫佢提供嗰個支援嘅。
服務噉，你當然係想佢可以喺嗰度攪到一啲生意，而佢攪到生意其實都係你嘅績效嚟啊嘛。咁如果你話就咁甩咗咧，就好嘥咯。噉我覺得可唔可以誒有啲file？如果或者你問翻佢睇下佢會唔會至少有啲基本嘅提供，又或者如果有啲file可能佢做到中間咧，佢再～
嗱，事實上，香港咧喺二零一七年，我冇估錯咧，就已經加入咗呢個亞投行嘅啦。譬如我咧，即係可能投資咗六十億港紙噉樣啦嚇。當時我咧都好期望咧，誒，即係可以用呢個亞投行咧，因為我哋香港係國際金融中心，亦都話亞洲最大嘅集資平台。
我哋希望呢個誒平台咧，能夠為嗰個誒一帶一路嘅企業嚇啊融資啊，誒甚至法制啊，亦都支持佢管理上嘅風險誒等等啊。誒同時咧，亦都希望即係誒香港係一個最大嘅誒全球。
一齊合作得到嘅，即係如果你好似內地。
法律服務啊、保險啊各方面，呢啲我哋係唔係真係可以？
如果你話一個好大嘅基建項目，佢係咪需要一定要通過香港咧？可能係不一定。
地嘅大企業，我哋點樣可以同呢啲大企業一齊合作？尤其是正話提及過啲專業服務嗰啲誒建築師啊。
嘅最後，我想問問啊副局咧，你即係講咧全政府動員嘅方針，除咗你商經局之外咧，我而家諗到咧就係誒財金局啦。
誒嘅企業去到傾去做，我哋嗰啲法律專業服務或者保險服務，佢點樣可以配入得到？定係佢哋或者我哋喺嗰度做，我都唔需要你哋香港個套。
法律制度，咁呢啲係咪真係受惠得到咧？同埋係咪有機會嗰啲融資、金融嘅融資係香港可以可以集資得到，而令到誒嗰啲資金可以喺嗰度發揮得到咧？
咁誒，我哋有啲乜嘢嘅成績喺呢方面喺嗰個資本市場呢方面有乜嘢嘅成績咧？同時當時我記得仲係一個希望咧，就係亞投行可唔可以喺呢度設一個營運嘅總部啊？嗰個當時嘅要求都好好，即係好多希望。
好多人都希望咧有呢個呢個噉嘅誒誒誒建議嘅，咁唔知誒而家咁多年過咗四五年之後咧，我哋呢方面嘅發展係點樣咧？唔該。係啊，邊位回答？或者我嘗試回應啊張議員嘅提問先啦。我好同意剛才啊張議員所講嘅，我哋。
係香港可以繼續發揮喺譬如剛才你所講嘅離岸人民幣中心方面嘅優勢啊，啊又或者係點樣樣係幫助內地同埋國際接軌啊呢個橋梁角色啊，噉啊配合我哋無論喺金融服務平台方面啦，又或者專業服務方面啦，啊投融資中心方面啦，啊資產管理啊，啊企業財
財財財資啊、風險管理啊、綠色金融等等呢啲項目咧，其實我哋係有呢方面嘅啊角色同優勢嘅。咁可能張議員都誒誒誒知道啦，就係我哋喺二零一六年咧，其實都成立咗啊ifl啦，嗰個係係金管局基建融資促進辦公室啦。咁其實當中咧，亦都係做咗好多嘅金融。
融項目或者投融資項目嘅對接嘅工作啦，咁譬如啊，誒誒，亦都係進行緊一個係啊基建貸款嘅證券化嘅工作啦。噉啊，希望可以進一步引導一啲嘅私人嘅市場嘅資金啦，去進入翻啊我哋成個誒比較啊呢啲基建項目嗰度嘅。咁喺呢方面嘅工作啦。
主席啊，誒，我想講咧，呢個一帶一路嘅基建咧，就喺誒，即係成成個嗰個誒區域嗰度咧，就有好多好多項目個，好多做緊嘅。誒，而且呢啲項目咧都係大企業，都牽涉嘅資金好大嘅。誒，噉我哋有冇主動？
去宣傳，誒，即係喺呢方面，我哋係香港係一個亞洲最大嘅集資平台，有冇叫佢哋喺呢度發債啊，甚至上市啊等等？我希望咧，大即係政府能夠主動去宣傳，做多啲功夫啦，就唔係淨係咧，即係我我哋有咗呢個機構噉就等等人嚟，我主動去要求去介。
誒裏邊好多細節內容嘅嘢都相對係抽象，所以點解正話周浩鼎議員同埋張麗雲議員都講咧，就係可唔可以有啲量化畀大家真係睇到，即係一帶一路過往咁多年誒專員，你哋嗰啲邊係做咗啲乜嘢，令到帶動到香。
香港嘅企業係受惠得到嘅，但係大家知道香港大部分中小企啦，我相信大部分中小企係而家喺點樣去跟住行，一但一路呢條路咧就相對，我我相對都唔容易嘅。噉啊，當然你就提及好多基建嗰啲咧，都好多都係誒國家內。
呢個啊朱言可唔可以？誒，其實其實啊，主席你你問嘅問題都係我每日諗緊嘅問題。誒，第一就係誒，如果係好大嘅基建項目咧，如果你睇翻佢哋啲融資啊各方面咧，佢可能係用翻國內嘅私路基金啊各方面，因為佢可以攞到國家。
官員。
誒。
咁下一個。
入嚟會議廳，噉啊，當局喺曾經咧就喺。
事實上，我相信係最大參與都係你同埋你個局同埋呢個財金局嘅啫喎，係咪啊？
好，噉我哋誒呢個議題討論到到此為止，噉啊多謝誒局方幾位官員。
收二十廿一括零六嘅文件，咁而咧就請投資推廣處幾位嘅。
項目就係促進外來嘅投資，噉啊！我哋而家又邀請投資推廣處嘅主要嘅官員。
誒投資推廣處嘅市場資訊主管孫海景先生，同埋商經局嘅助理秘書長羅家榮女士。
噉我哋會有投資推廣處處長誒傅仲森先生，就助理處長鄧志良先生，同埋。
誒二零二零年就介紹，即係介紹個二零二零年嘅工作報告噉嘅。今日咧就將會係講講咧未來二零二一同至到二零二二年嘅工作嘅計劃。
噉啊，當局就準備咗啲討論嘅文件啦，就係CB庫一八九零縮二十廿一庫零五，同埋秘書處咧就準備咗啲背景文件就係CB庫一八九零。
咁仲有咩局我哋真係可以參與到呢個一帶一路啲所謂全政府動員？因為你講到全政府動員咧，不如個感覺咧就好大嘅，成個政府奮身落去。但係事實上係咪咁咧？
嘅補助，咁如果依啲噉嘅項目咧，我哋講融資咧，香港係比較難參與嘅，因為佢有啲國家補助啊，呢三十五年嘅貸款。咁但係頭先啊，局長都講過，就係我哋希望推動嘅咧，就係喺誒專業團隊入邊嘅企業咧。
誒，尤其是啲中小企業可以係跟住呢啲項目誒嘅其中一環走。我哋唔係好貪心，就希望全個大嘅項目咧誒，香港企業都參與。咁所以，我哋一路要求誒，或者係誒希望國家支持咧，就係誒。
所有啲對接，誒包括省份嘅對接，誒包括我哋誒唔同嘅專業團隊，包括金融啊，頭先講保險業啊，誒律師團隊啊嘅貢貢獻。咁其實有一個好誒大嘅重點咧，我覺得就係誒大部分嗰啲央企。
甚至有啲民企係做呢啲基建項目咧，佢哋都係中意喺香港作為佢嘅國際中心嘅，即係佢國際總部。噉我哋最近誒亦都做咗好多嘢，就係譬如誒誒呢啲噉嘅誒公司，佢係做緊即係國際嘅總部。
我喺香港嘅話咧，我哋點樣可以令到佢更加利用香港嘅公司嘅對接？我哋都做緊，包括上個禮拜我哋做嘅就係其實揾咗好多係誒央企喺誒國際嘅總部嘅香港代表誒，同翻我哋啲專業企業。
包括頭先講I F F O，我哋都有揾咗I F F O嚟誒講翻我哋嘅做法，亦都包括頭先講嘅誒保險業嘅風險管理中心喺香港。咁依依啲一要一步一步嚟，就係誒我哋希望係誒越嚟越多嘅可以做到量化依個誒誒依個企業，但係。
明白誒，多謝主席嘅提問啦。誒，全政府參與嗰方面啦，其實以往我哋就住一啲嘅，譬如專責小組啊，或者係一啲嘅誒同國家誒商務部啊、法改委啊一啲嘅合作嘅會議裏邊啦，其實我哋都會邀請啊，譬如CMAB誒內地及政制事務局啦去參與啦。咁剛才我。
我回應嗰時都有講啦，誒一帶一路同埋大灣區嘅發展啦，其實係一個雙引擎嚟嘅。噉我哋喺宣傳一帶一路嘅過程當中咧，亦都會好好咁利用翻大灣區呢方面嘅優勢。咁所以我哋亦都係會誒邀請啊CMAB嘅同事去參與啦，當中啊包括就係我剛才所講嘅一啲嘅外訪活動啊，嚟緊無。
誒。
Stephen Tois。
projects came from a diverse range of sectors.
哦，Mr. Chairman，Thank you very much indeed.
The project created almost 8,000 jobs.
They came from 34 economies.
So quickly, the highlights of our results for two thousand and twenty.
followed by the UK, the US, Japan, and Singapore.
by the number of projects, the mainland continued to be the largest source of investment.
And then set out our strategies for inward investment promotion in the remainder of 2021-22.
噉啊！我先請誒投資推廣處處長介紹一下今日嘅討論嘅嘅文件，好唔好啊？
一重組化，那Invest Hong Kong， has just undertaken， really responding to changing market dynamics and needs。
Turning to the reorganisation of Invest Hong Kong, to respond to the changing market dynamics, we put in place a reorganisation on the one of April this year.
但最高數字係在金融科技、創新和科技，和business and professional services sectors，所以Quite a shift actually in terms of the sector mix。
Against the context of the challenging global environment, and in particular because of the COVID-19 pandemic, I'd like to share with panel members the highlights of our results for 2020.
We assisted 317 overseas and mainland companies to set up or expand in Hong Kong, and that compared to 487 in 2019. The drop is a direct correlation with the COVID environment.
無論線上又好、線下又好，我哋都會邀請佢參與啦。另外就係話投資推廣處呢度啊，當然咧呢個都係阿阿Under我哋商經局啦，但係我哋亦都會邀請佢啊作為點樣去引資或引其他企業係嚟香港呢個動作啦。我哋都會邀請佢一同參與我哋一啲嘅宣傳項目啊，一啲嘅工作嘅。好多謝噉啊，時間啱啱。
I'd now like to quickly share our approach to inward investment promotion.
所以，轉換到我們策略， for investment promotion。
Investments and other business activities have been significantly impacted.
The largest volume coming from financial services and family offices, followed by innovation and technology.
That said, in the first four months of 2021, we saw 106 projects complete across all sectors.
With anti-pandemic measures, including border control and quarantine requirements, imposed all around the world.
Furthermore, we're going to deploy technology to both internal and external processes to meet the needs of our clients and drive productivity and efficiency.
The development of family offices businesses, talent attraction and leveraging digital platforms, both for our external work and internally.
We do know that some investors have put their investment plans on hold, while some are seeing new opportunities in the changed and challenging times.
anticipated economic growth in Asia, the development of Greater Bay Area, RCEP and the Belt and Road Initiative, will all add impetus to the interest.
Based upon our continuous global outreach, we believe that many foreign and mainland investors will gradually resume their investment plans as when travel restrictions ease.
In a few words, the overall environment, the COVID pandemic, obviously has given significant rise to uncertainties in the global macroeconomic environment, and indeed outlook.
The business development group includes redeployment of existing resources to the incredibly important Greater Bay Area development, and also the Belt and Road Initiative to generate maximum impact.
一新國際主land和Greater Bay Area Business Development Group has been set up to leverage our representatives around the globe, as well as the international and local networks such as chambers and consulates.
Under the new structure, the nine sector teams all come under the sector specialist group in three broad areas, and this is both for greater synergy and to recognise the growing convergence of sectors, driven by technology.
The new structure is our response to a changing environment, and also reflecting in best Hong Kong's priority areas, including initiatives featured in the Chief Executive's 2020 policy address, and those include the Greater Bay Area Inward Investment Team.
和策略性研究。
會被launch publicly very soon.
一個dedicated microsite to help them.
Maybe I could just say a few words about our active role in major national initiatives.
as well as sharing as best practices, and that will be on a global level, once travel resumes.
They enhance Hong Kong's role as a two-way development base for going global and attracting foreign investment.
The mainland, of course, is a key engine of global economic growth and a key market for all of the work at Invest Hong Kong.
Flagship Start Me Up Hong Kong Festival will be going ahead next week, and that will be followed by the FinTech Week in November.
And we'll continue to strengthen our online and targeted promotional activities in priority areas, for instance, around the Greater Bay Area, innovation and technology, and family offices.
The opportunities brought by the 14th Five-Year Plan, Greater Bay Area development, and the Belt and Road initiatives are elements of Hong Kong's inward investment proposition. Right at the very core of it.
The dedicated Greater Bay Area Business Development Team that I've mentioned is very much focused on attracting international companies to invest in the Greater Bay Area via Hong Kong.
We've been dynamically adjusting our strategy, really week by week, and very much leveraging digital platforms to reach out to investors in both traditional and emerging markets.
We've really strengthened the liaison with overseas chambers and consulates in Hong Kong to further the outreach to foreign businesses already here, including the provision of additional aftercare support.
We deploy an integrated marketing strategy. Social media is at the forefront of what we do, supplemented by more traditional means: advertising, publications, public relations activities, events.
The team has also started discussions with our mainland counterparts on the establishment of a Pan Greater Bay Area Investment Liaison Group, and the aim of that is to have joint propositions, joint marketing materials, joint events.
We'll continue to take proactive and targeted approach in identifying and inviting specific investors to set up here in Hong Kong. And in doing so, we continue to work with other bureaux and departments, as well as key partners in Hong Kong Inc, as well as overseas ETOs.
啊！
thank you, Stephen.
考慮或者計劃離開香港，佢答。
第二個問題就係誒。
旅遊嘅項目嘅一啲嘅誒地盤或者地基地啦。
We're also engaging with many key industry stakeholders around the Greater Bay opportunity.
誒咁誒，第一位姚思榮議員，我又唔設時間限制住，因為有充足時間。
國家文化旅遊部咧喺舊年就提出咗《粵港澳大灣區文化和旅遊發展規劃》。
To wrap up, perhaps I could just say a few words about resumption of physical face-to-face work once the pandemic subsides and a more stable business environment returns.
會definitely be the first people jumping on a plane, jumping on a train, to have face-to-face meetings, to proactively attract and assist overseas and mainland companies to set up in Hong Kong.
公司或者大嘅一啲有誒旅遊經驗嘅，即係旅遊景點經驗嘅一啲集團咧，去對香港嘅一啲誒旅遊規劃作出一啲即係誒推廣或者吸引佢哋嚟香港投資咧噉樣。
Finally, our target for completed projects for this coming year is 345, reflecting the challenging pandemic environment. But I'd like to ensure panel members that I and my colleagues will do all we can to bring in additional investment to the city. Thank you very much.
唔該，葉思榮議員。誒，多謝主席。就有關嗰個誒，最近美國商會咧，就對佢哋嘅會員作出一個調查啊。噉啊，雖然回應嘅比例度唔係好高，有百分之廿四啦，但係咧都當中有四十二個percent嘅會員咧會考。
咁另外有百分之三嘅會員咧，打算馬上就要離開香港㗎啦。咁呢個調查咧，對我哋香港投資方面帶嚟咗乜嘢負面嘅影響咧？政府喺呢方面有冇作出一個研究，或者將來有喺呢對呢方面有咩回應咧？噉樣？
調查。
That that has brought.
兩個問題啊，係啊。
which we're engaging with the chamber community and the business community on constantly.
within the 14th five-year plan as well, and Hong Kong has very important role to play in that.
Obviously, we have Art Basel in Hong Kong as a flagship event, but many, many.
On the culture and tourism side, it is a very important area for our work. Obviously, culture features very strongly.
As the secretary said, he and indeed invest Hong Kong, hear a great deal from the international business community on an ongoing basis.
We are seeing a lot of activity in the art space. Hong Kong really has become a major international art centre.
And from the government point of view, we're very grateful for those surveys, and it helps to have a pulse on the international business community sentiment in Hong Kong.
Galleries from around the world in Hong Kong as well, and that's just one dimension of it. Clearly, the West Kowloon District will be a big driver of the development of the cultural industries.
And certainly, what we have heard is, in particularly in 2019, with all of the social unrest, and then with the national security law following, that companies really do welcome the stability.
In terms of themed attractions, I think that would be something where we would target investors if we knew that there was a significant developmental opportunity in Hong Kong for a newly themed investment.
I think when you look at the AmCham survey as well, it is worth distinguishing that that is talking about individuals as opposed to companies. So it's two quite distinct features. Of course, it's something that as government we're watching very closely.
咁香港喺整個文化旅遊方面咧，其實係一個起咗一個重相當重要嘅角色。而本身我哋亦有唔少嘅資源嘅，譬如西九文化區啦、誒迪士尼嘅二期啦，或者將來大嶼山嘅欣澳都可能會係未來發展旅。
喺呢方面，政府就未來引進投資方面咧，就旅遊與款待方面，除咗好似舊年剩嘅一啲即係飲食啊、零售方面之外咧，喺大型嘅呢啲投資，政府會唔會再進一步物色誒向海外或者內地揾一啲大？
Okay, thank you very much indeed. I think on the AnChan survey, the Secretary for Economic Development commented very sensibly last week. Over the last year or two, we've seen a lot of chambers doing peer
But when we look at the wider spectrum of chambers and businesses with whom we engage, we're not seeing any significant volumes of people intending to leave. But clearly, it's something that we will continue to follow up very closely, and.
哼。
sorry。
傾向。
唔該啊，主席。
佢都有個重點咧，佢話。
有冇嘢跟隨啊？O.K.跟住啊，張麗雲議員。
我唔知有冇其他嗰啲商會都係有噉樣講法。
佢話：假如日後要去大誒，即係大灣區成個大市場發展咧。
誒嗰個早前咧就係誒。
誒，即係可能會係有啲人會係。
噉啊，而當中咧，我我就留意到美國商會會長阿Tara咧。
成本等等咧，都係會平過香港嘅噉樣，咁所以因因此會唔會？
It certainly isn't something that we would do without having the basis to hold the conversation with such company.
啊嘛！阿姚議員亦都問到咧，就係話誒美國商會嗰度咧，有超過四成嘅受訪者話佢哋可能會走喎，噉啊！
啊，處長咧就都有啊提及過啦，就係話誒，即係佢唔覺得啊，即係香港一啲外來投資者咧會係啊有離開嘅跡象嚇，好似上次會議都講過嘅。噉啊，但係最近啱啱。
咁咧係有可能咧，就一啲企業咧就可能會選擇就去大灣區，而唔嚟唔留喺香港。咁因為大灣區個居住成本啊，同埋嗰個誒呢一個overhead，即係嗰個誒有好多嘅開支啦，係勞動。
Hey Stephen.
To put it one way.
And it really will be dependent upon what their business strategy is.
and about their inability to go and visit family who live overseas.
所以那些係兩 Quite Different Things in terms of the work that we do. So it's about talent rather than about investment.
In so far as companies relocating, for instance, to the Greater Bay Area or to Singapore.
I think for most companies, it is very rarely a binary choice between two locations.
即係假如係有啲真係咁諗法嘅話，我哋會唔會考慮？即係都要睇點樣可以，即係誒。
always this very complicated pattern that's quite hard to put your finger on in a data sense, but what we see in our day-to-day work.
In terms of what we hear from other chambers, we hear some concerns, particularly around families who are concerned about the education of their children.
係將間公司誒假誒一係就離開成個大灣區香港，咪搬去新加坡或者其他地方。但係亦都有啲人咧，假如佢中意留低嚇呢個大灣區融合嘅話咧，佢可能會唔會入咗去裏邊咧咁？
Of course, there's always an ebb and flow of businesses. Some businesses leave, some businesses will close, but all the time new businesses continue to arrive. And as I said, we've had over a hundred companies, even in the first four months of this year, set up in the city.
誒預先做定一啲工作嚇，咁即係確保我哋即係香港啊，依然有一啲優勢存在啦。噉樣係咪咁同埋喺呢度咧？我諗我哋係咪誒又未來會唔會考慮啊？處長會唔會考慮做啲研究咧？唔該。
Thank you very much indeed. I think all I would say again on the AMCHAM survey is it is a survey of individuals, so it's the intention of individuals, perhaps of their families, as opposed to the intention of the corporate entity.
But generally speaking, when we look at the intention of investors, we're not seeing any material change to what we've seen over many years in terms of the intention of companies to continue to operate a business in Hong Kong.
And again, we see no evidence that people are sort of shipping or packing up bags and moving wholesale to one location or another. And what isn't reported is other companies that relocate from another regional city back to Hong Kong. So there's all.
and hence the sophistication of our work.
within them, but not to the extent of the AmCham survey.
with them, they do broader base surveys that may have one or two questions.
I think it's very difficult to put that in a one-size-fits-all proposition.
所以，它係關於質素的建議和支持，我們提供，我認為係會造成差別。
delve very deeply into understanding both the objectives of business, what their constraints may be.
We do really have some very sophisticated propositions on a sector by sector basis.
In terms of ensuring that Hong Kong still remains a very favoured destination.
The unique advantages of the rule of law and common law system in Hong Kong. These are all very important factors.
But also our knowledge of what the opportunity is in Hong Kong, Greater Bay Area, the whole of the country, and indeed in ASEAN, and for some companies, Belt and Road.
所以，ordinarily when we're talking to a company, we can provide them with bespoke advice as to what the pros and cons of a certain approach is.
where we outline to companies the natural advantages of Hong Kong as a very international centre, both in Asia and of course as the most international city within the country.
誒誒，我我阿Sir嚟講，啱啱聽唔到，都好清楚係你話其他嗰啲誒商會，其他國家嘅商會，誒佢哋有冇誒都有啲噉嘅講法，佢哋好多人會走，好多會員會走呢一樣嘢，你有冇聽到咧？
And for companies that are looking at a pan-Asian strategy, Hong Kong offers many, many more advantages than trying to do that. Let's say from a location in a very big market where the team is focused on those opportunities.
As far as I know, the American Chamber is the only chamber that has done a dedicated survey looking at the intention of the individuals. The other chambers, we hear the information rather more informally and anecdotally in our ongoing engagement.
really has to.
近呢一兩年咧，就確實咧。
誒，我哋畀一啲。
In terms of the
誒，我絕對認同張議員你嗰個睇法。
啊，噉啊，誒係啦，呢個好重要啦。咁另外仲有一樣嘢咧。
嚇，噉就誒誒，即係或者係誒。
that we see in both sectors and by geography to colleagues across government.
我哋香港依然係一個非常非常好嘅經商城市，唔該。
And then we work with colleagues in the relevant bureau to try and find solutions, and we'll continue to do that.
O.K.，嗯，我我我諗主席，我哋都誒知道香港其中一樣係同內地嘅城市係好唔同，因為香港係一個國際都會啦。
噉就但係，即係，所以我哋喺呢方面，我覺得誒都希望誒投資推廣處啦，或者政府方面啦，嚇都能夠係關心嚇一啲真係香港做生意嘅投資嘅外國商人。
And with specific cases where a company or the staff members involved are facing problems, we will elevate that to senior levels within the government. So that's something that really is part and parcel of our aftercare service.
誒一啲人啊嚇，一啲其他嘅一一啲國家咧，咁咧就有啲國家咧就係形容到香港好似冇咗自由，誒即係亦都誒即係好似講到香港已經成為誒中好似中國誒內地嘅其中一個城市噉樣啊！
誒能夠係誒，假如見到任何嘅跡象啊，或者係佢哋嘅生活上啊，或者點樣咧，我都希望咧，處長能夠及早將個情況或者係點樣反映畀誒，即係政府啊，即係高層嗰啲知道啦，係嘛？
咁但係事實上，我哋好清楚，我哋香港依然擁有高度、高度嘅自由、金融嘅自由嚇。咁所以，我覺得啊，處長你都應該誒考慮喺呢度誒，即係能夠做多啲宣傳啊，畀人哋世界各地都知道。
嗯，thank you.
rest of the region.
誒將。
So，I have several questions.
and that targeted approach on.
Clearly, that filters through to the businesses that we're talking to.
regarding to the same questions that honorary
negative headlines that we see in the media around the world that we hear in political circles around the world.
In terms of trying to change that media narrative, we work with other parts of government, including information services departments.
在The events that we do at Invest Hong Kong， we drive home these messages all around the world about the reality of the situation on the ground。
dealing with decision makers and making sure that decision makers know the reality is much better time and effort spent by me and my team than us trying to change a global media narrative.
But I think it would be fair to say that the businesses that we talk to are rather more worldly wise than just reading the headlines. So these are informed people who do their homework, do their research.
所以， they look beyond the headline. So, whilst it doesn't help with the the broad perception, I can say with a degree of confidence that the companies we're talking to have a much better understanding of the reality.
Gamma, is there any replies from you, Stephen, about what? Yes, certainly in terms of the sentiment of investors or any challenges or hurdles that they're facing. On a regular basis, we report generically on overall sentiment.
And we will share very frankly with companies what we see, and we'll explain if there's a particular headline that a company raises with us, we'll provide the counter side of the story and explain what the situation is.
But as we all know, that's a very challenging job. So what we're trying to do is get good news stories about successes that we see in Hong Kong out there. A whole series of events, sorry, pieces in media where we're
presenting what's going on in the startup scene, conveying the exciting developments in the Greater Bay Area, to subtly get across actually what an exciting city Hong Kong is and the wealth of opportunity that there is from Hong Kong, whether it's in the country or the
do you?
所以。
呢 sort of。
actively approach.
was asking.
the business sector, the international business sector.
you you know right now the Western world especially the Western government.
since you are here, you cannot go go away. and how does
And typically, that would be raised with one of our teams outside Hong Kong.
which you just explained, but do you actively approach them and tell them this is not the real fact?
with the facts and other colleagues do that all of the time, so that's very targeted, very focused on a particular issue, and that a company raises.
questions how how do you tackle and explain to the international business sector that the Hong Kong hasn't changed that much.
I think there's a range of ways in which we do this. The smallest volume is where companies raise a specific issue or a specific concern with us.
The office you have in the overseas approach them and explain the real situations. Especially there's misleading concept about the new national security law and our new election systems. They
Having some misleading message, as you said, the other national media also having some misleading message, telling the whole world that Hong Kong's change, Hong Kong right now is similar to a local city in China, but actually we are not.
But those teams would very quickly elevate that issue to us in Hong Kong if they're finding that they're not persuading the company of the information. And I have joined personally many conversations with such businesses to give them the view as I see it here and present them.
哦，OK。
到香港，和少 Overseas。
所以，依，
在The Capital Flows that we see, what's published by the HKMA and so forth.
所以，喺《The Regional Headquarters Survey》、《That We Do》、《In The Startup Survey》。
I do hope you you can do a better job to directly approach.
or or the other way round, more overseas company coming to Hong Kong, and what was the proportions or the ratio?
Those conversations tend to be quite interactive, and we'll address these questions as they crop up in the discussion.
We then have a lot of engagement at roundtable level, so maybe only a dozen companies that we're talking to.
Companies from other parts of the world generally falling. So, it's been an overall trending upwards, but the mainland at a faster pace than elsewhere.
它會給 quite a lot of ammunition to address either a particular concern or demonstrate that actually the reality is quite different to some of that media narrative.
and in certainly every meeting event that I do, I will tackle these issues upfront and say you'll have seen the headlines. Let me address the situation as I see it and take people through the reality.
And then obviously answer any questions that they have. And in the bigger events, we also talk about the reality of the situation in Hong Kong. And we do this both in terms of describing day to day what we see, but also what we see in the day.
The important business international business sector， so that they understand us more。Well，from from the paper paragraph three， I've noticed that there is a survey， annual survey of company in Hong Kong with parents company located outside Hong Kong， conduct jointly by Mas Hong Kong。
There is the saying that there are nine thousand twenty five overseas and mainland companies in in Hong Kong in two thousand and twenty. Do you have the figures of how many is from the overseas and how many from the mainland? Because I want because I want to note whether there are more mainland company are coming.
Yeah, we we certainly do have breakdown, and my colleagues will share those with you in a second. Obviously, the number of companies have been increasing. The share of mainland investments by number of companies has been growing, but not to the detriment of.
嗯。
在阿森國或或其他 major。
但perhaps Vincent can share some of the detail.
We want to build Hong Kong to be the global family office in Asia.
所以，for instance， in the Middle East， where an economic trade office will open in Dubai。
And then we'll be working with our local offices there, so it's a slightly different model for the region.
The team is being built out. As you said, we'll have dedicated staff, not only in Hong Kong, but Guangzhou, Beijing and Brussels.
However, staff in other locations globally will also have a certain amount of their time focused on the family office initiative.
The last question I have is about the family office. I mean, I think this is the trend of building another new new industries in Hong Kong. But according to the information you have,
later this year, one of the members of staff, part of the job spec for them, will be around family offices. So we'll be looking for somebody with relevant experience for that, and the Middle East is a big focus for us.
都係主席。其實嗰九千零二十五間嘅，即係國內或者海外公司咧，我哋都有一個詳細嘅一個嘅誒分類嘅。咁當中咧就係有接近二千間，即係一千九百八十六間咧，係由國內內地喺香港開嘅誒，一係總公司啦，一係就誒地區公司啦噉啊。
啊！或者地區嘅主要嘅一個分公司，咁而接住落嚟咧，就係第二多嘅咧，就係由日本啊，日本當中咧有接近一千四百間由日本嚟香港開嘅公司。咁跟住就係美國啦、英國啦、新加坡、德國啊噉樣。咁所以我哋呢個統計上面嘅數字咧，就誒每年我哋都會做嘅。
亦都有一個好誒統計嘅一個仔細嘅，即係每個國家由邊度嚟。咁但係過去一段非常之長嘅時間一直以嚟咧，其實都係由國內嚟嘅公司咧，都係佔咧就所有我哋所誒公司咧，海外或者國內嘅公司咧，都係排第一嘅。所以呢個數字上面咧都幾穩定。好啊，唔該曬。
So how how would you compare our competitiveness to the other countries like the compared our competitor in Singapore? And and how comes that you you have a global family office team in Beijing, Guangzhou and Brussels? And why why why don't you have anything in?
Countries like US or Japan. Thank you. Well, the family office initiative is new, and in fact, our first member of dedicated staff started last week. We'll have dedicated office space, which we've just taken possession of this week.
In terms of ASEAN, we decided that having a critical mass of colleagues based in Hong Kong was the way to approach the ASEAN market. So, colleagues based in Hong Kong will be travelling to ASEAN.
署長，can can you誒？
In terms of relative competitiveness.
Okay, thank you。跟住啊，蔣麗雲議員係咪第二輪啊？
Of helping family offices tap into investment opportunities.
Obviously, within the region, Singapore is well known as a family office hub.
In recent months, there's been a number of very significant policy developments in Hong Kong.
policy and regulatory environment is world class to ensure that we're well positioned, as well as the more practical parts.
或者淨係做顧問啊，或者點樣可以作一啲分類咯，清楚少少嚇。咁唔該。好唔好嘅？
From listed all the way through to early stage, but also alternative asset classes, and this is actually where it loops back to the art and cultural side because.
The limited partnership fund structure, which has been introduced, is very significant. The recent legislation for carried interest also very significant.
噉啊，冇其他委員再發問咧，我哋就今日呢個議題到此為止，好嘛？Thank you, Stephen and your team. Thank you.
In terms of new investments in Hong Kong, yes, we we do have that information and we can share that. So we've got that both historically, and we keep it going forward as well. Okay, thank you. Okay.
the the art side actually is a very interesting alternative asset class in Hong Kong, so there's a connection with building up the family office ecosystem, with further building up Hong Kong as an international art centre.
And of course, that's where Hong Kong wins out in terms of access to mainland-related investment opportunities. So there's an element of work that will be around ensuring that the overall.
So pieces from a policy point of view being put in place to ensure that Hong Kong is competitive both at a technical and financial level, as well as competitive in terms of access to investment opportunities.
好，同你。我我一句就就要求，即係誒下一次可唔可以咧？就係佢可以將嗰啲誒新嚟嘅投資嗰啲咧，嗰啲人咧能誒，即係嗰啲誒誒咩行係做咩行業？譬如話金融類嘅誒，或者trading貿易啊。
誒，如果冇其他委員提出其他事項，我就宣佈會議結束。多謝大家。